Guide to the Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part III WAG.025.003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series V: Departments, Chapters, and Divisions, 1940-2009
  - Subseries E: Educators' Chapter, 1943-2008
    The JLC's commitment to promoting Holocaust education is also documented through its collection of educational resources in the form of curriculum guides, published materials such as books and plays, and audiovisual media.
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1985-1987, 1985-1993, undated (Box 384)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1985-1990, 1985-1990, undated (Box 385)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1988-1989, 1985-1990 (Box 393)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1987-1992, 1985-1995, undated (Box 403)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1988-1990, 1986-1991 (Box 386)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1991-1993, 1990-1993, undated (Box 373)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1993-1996, 1985-1996, undated (Box 401)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program, 1996-1997, 1973, 1989-1998, undated (Box 402)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program: Assorted Subjects, 1943, 1963, 1967-1974, 1984-2001, undated (Box 400)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program: Master Chronological Files, 1991-1995 (Box 408)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program and First and Second National Alumni Conferences, 1985-1989, undated (Box 404)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program and National Alumni Conferences: Photographs, 1994-1998 (Box 405)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program: Photographs (Oversize), undated; 1 folder (Box 507)
    - Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program: Scrapbook for Vladka Meed, 1989; 1 item (Box 501)
    - Holocaust Education Resources, circa 1987, 1998-1999, undated; 3 folders (Box 402)
    - Holocaust Education Resources, 1988-1999, undated; 9 folders (Box 404)
    - Holocaust Education Resources, 1973, 1979, 1986-1999, undated (Box 407)
    - Holocaust Education Resources: CD and CR-ROM, 1993, 1999; 2 items (Box 533)
    - Holocaust Education Resources: Audiocassette Tapes and Rolled Negative, 1976, 1989, 1993-1998, undated; 7 items (Box 523)
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Building Holocaust Education-- Teaching Trunks", 1999; 1 item
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Requiem-- The Holocaust", 1993; 1 item
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Annuan Weinmann Lecture-- 'Survivors - and Success - in American Business'", 1998; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Holocaust Museum/St. Louis NPR Weekend Edition Saturday", 1998; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Night Thieves of the Warsaw Ghetto", 1995; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Oklahoma-- Together We'll Ride", 1989; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "Resistance (Board of Jewish Education of Greater New York)", 1976; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: "National Catholic Educational Association (NCEA) 90th Annual Convention", 1993; 1 audiocassette
    - Holocaust Education Resources: VHS Tapes, circa 1988-1997; 24 videocassettes (Box 497)
    - Holocaust Education Resources: VHS Tapes and U-matic Tape, circa 1988-1997; 25 videocassettes (Box 498)
    - First and Second National Alumni Conferences, 1987-1989 (Box 394)
    - First Alumni Conference: Audio, 1988; 10 audiocassettes (Box 517)
    - Second Alumni Conference: Audio, 1989; 7 audiocassettes (Box 517)
    - Second Alumni Conference: Audio, 1989 (Box 518)
    - Second Alumni Conference: Audio, 1989; 8 audiocassettes (Box 519)
    - Second and Third National Alumni Conferences, 1988-1990 (Box 395)
    - Third Alumni Conference: Audio, 1990; 3 audiocassettes (Box 520)
    - Fourth and Fifth National Alumni Conferences, 1990-1992 (Box 396)
    - Fourth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1991; 5 audiocassettes (Box 519)
    - Fifth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1992; 4 audiocassettes (Box 519)
    - Fifth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1992; 10 audiocassettes (Box 520)
    - Fifth through Seventh National Aumni Conferences, 1991-1996 (Box 397)
    - Sixth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1994; 7 audiocassettes (Box 520)
    - Sixth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1994; 13 audiocassettes (Box 521)
    - Seventh through Ninth Alumni Conferences, 1995-2000 (Box 398)
    - Seventh Alumni Conference: Audio, 1996; 5 audiocassettes (Box 521)
    - Seventh Alumni Conference: Audio, 1996; 2 audiocassettes (Box 511)
    - Eighth Alumni Conference: Audio, 1998; 4 audiocassettes (Box 510)
    - Ninth through Thirteenth Alumni Conferences, 1999-2008 (Box 399)
    - National Alumni Conferences: Convention Packets, 1989-2008 (Box 534)
    - Holocaust Studies Alumni by State (Card Files), undated (Box 523)
- Series VI: Jewish Labour Committee, Canada, 1948-1978
  The Jewish Labour Committee, Canada was founded in 1936. Like the U.S. JLC, the Canadian JLC was heavily involved in relief efforts during and in the aftermath of World War II, both by providing aid in Europe and sponsoring refugees who came to Canada.
  In the post-war period, the organization focused on combatting discrimination in Canadian society. Various laws prohibiting discrimination in areas such as housing, education, race, and employment were passed in response to the Canadian JLC's investigations and other forms of activism. In 1947, the Canadian JLC merged with the Joint Public Relations Committee to form the Joint Advisory Committee on Labour Relations, with JLC Executive Director Kalmen Kaplansky as its leader.
  The Canadian JLC dissolved in 1978.
  The records of the Jewish Labour Committee, Canada reflect the organization's parallels to the U.S. JLC in its affiliations and activities, particularly in its anti-discrimination campaigns. The series includes minutes of the Canadian JLC's governing bodies, reports and press releases created by the Canadian Jewish Congress and the Canadian Labour Congress, correspondence with the U.S. JLC, and convention materials. The largest group of files concerning local activities is devoted to Montreal, whose large Jewish community (including many Holocaust survivors) had close ties to the JLC in the United States. The series also contains material on labor and civil rights issues in Canada more generally.
  The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Canada, 1948-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Canada: General, 1958-1969, undated (Box 193, Folder 1-8)
  - Canada: General, 1976-1978 (Box 193, Folder 8A)
  - Canada: JLC Archival Material, 1978 (Box 193, Folder 8B)
  - Canada: Montreal, 1951; 2 folders (Box 392)
  - Canada: Reports, 1947-1955; 2 folders (Box 392)
  - L'Accord, 1965-1967 (Box 193, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1960 (Box 193, Folder 10)
  - Bilingualism, 1964-1965 (Box 193, Folder 11)
  - Blum, Sid, undated (Box 193, Folder 12)
  - Book Lists, 1961 (Box 193, Folder 13)
  - Borovoy, Al, 1967 (Box 193, Folder 14)
  - British Columbia, undated (Box 193, Folder 15)
  - Bulletin (English), 1975-1976 (Box 193, Folder 16)
  - Bulletin (Yiddish), 1965-1968 (Box 193, Folder 17)
  - Canadian Citizenship Council, 1960 (Box 193, Folder 18)
  - Canadian Committee for World Refugee Year, 1959-1960 (Box 193, Folder 19)
  - Canadian Conference on Education, 1962 (Box 193, Folder 20)
  - Canadian Jewish Congress, 1952-1954; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Canadian Jewish Congress, 1958-1967 (Box 193, Folder 21-24)
  - Canadian Jewish Congress Bulletin, 1960-1961 (Box 193, Folder 25)
  - Canadian Labour Congress, 1952-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Canadian Labour Congress, 1958-1959 (Box 193, Folder 26-28)
  - Canadian Labour Congress, 1960-1977 (Box 194, Folder 1-2)
  - Canadian Labour Congress: Bulletins, 1960-1962 (Box 194, Folder 3)
  - Carpenters: Newfoundland, 1962 (Box 194, Folder 4)
  - Chanin, Nahum, undated (Box 194, Folder 5)
  - Citizens' Commission on Human Rights, 1958 (Box 194, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1964-1970 (Box 194, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: Discrimination, Hate Literature, etc., 1947-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Clippings: Discrimination, Hate Literature, etc., 1957-1970 (Box 194, Folder 8)
  - Commission on Intergroup Relations (COIR), 1960-1961 (Box 194, Folder 9)
  - Confederation of National Trade Unions, 1963 (Box 194, Folder 10)
  - Conference, 1950; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Construction Unions, 1960 (Box 194, Folder 11)
  - Conventions, 1951-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Conventions, 1960-1965 (Box 194, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1978; 3 folders (Box 194, Folder 13-15)
  - Correspondence: with JLC USA, 1957-1961 (Box 194, Folder 16-25)
  - Department of Labour reports, 1962-1965 (Box 194, Folder 26-27)
  - Discrimination: General, 1959-1967 (Box 194, Folder 28)
  - Discrimination in Employment, 1957-1965 (Box 194, Folder 29)
  - Discrimination: Reports, 1961 (Box 194, Folder 30)
  - Dresden, Ontario, 1955; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Erlich, Henryk and Viktor Alter, 1961-1962 (Box 194, Folder 31)
  - Executive, 1962 (Box 194, Folder 32)
  - Finances, 1967-1973 (Box 195, Folder 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1948-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Financial Reports, 1957-1974 (Box 195, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising, 1968 (Box 195, Folder 3)
  - "Gateway" (Documentary Film), 1972 (Box 195, Folder 4)
  - Gandhi Memorial, 1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Grape Boycott, 1968-1969 (Box 195, Folder 5)
  - Hate Literature, 1965 (Box 195, Folder 6)
  - Hate Propaganda, 1966-1969 (Box 195, Folder 7)
  - Housing, 1959-1961 (Box 195, Folder 8)
  - Human Rights, 1958-1968 (Box 195, Folder 9)
  - Human Rights Anniversary Committee, 1958 (Box 195, Folder 10)
  - Human Rights: Nova Scotia, 1967 (Box 195, Folder 11)
  - Human Rights: Ontario, 1965-1969 (Box 195, Folder 12)
  - Hungary, 1951; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Immigration, 1957-1968 (Box 195, Folder 13)
  - Indians, 1960-1967 (Box 195, Folder 14)
  - Indian-Eskimo Association of Canada, 1963-1965 (Box 195, Folder 15)
  - Iraq, 1969-1971 (Box 195, Folder 16)
  - "Jew in French Canada:" Viewpoints, 1969 (Box 195, Folder 17)
  - Jewish Labour Bund (Canada), 1970 (Box 195, Folder 18)
  - Joint Advisory Committee on Labour Relations, 1947-1956; 2 folders (Box 392)
  - Joint Advisory Committee on Labour Relations, 1957-1968 (Box 195, Folder 19-21)
  - Joint Advisory Committee on Labour Relations: Reports, 1949-1954; 4 folders (Box 392)
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr., undated (Box 195, Folder 22)
  - Labour Committee Against Racial Intolerance, 1950-1955; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Labour Committee against Racial intolerance, 1957-1961 (Box 195, Folder 23)
  - Labor Legislation, 1959-1961 (Box 195, Folder 24)
  - Lehrer, Leib, undated (Box 195, Folder 25)
  - Mackenzie Valley Pipeline Inquiry, 1976 (Box 195, Folder 26)
  - Manitoba, 1961 (Box 195, Folder 27)
  - Middle East, 1957 (Box 195, Folder 28)
  - Minutes: National Executive, 1962-1975 (Box 195, Folder 29)
  - Minutes: Office Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 195, Folder 30)
  - Montreal, 1947-1955; 11 folders (Box 392)
  - Montreal, 1957-June 1966 (Box 195, Folder 31-39)
  - Montreal, August 1966-1977 (Box 196, Folder 1-7)
  - Montreal Labour Committee on Human Rights, 1961 (Box 196, Folder 8)
  - National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials (NAIRO), 1961-1963 (Box 196, Folder 9)
  - National Civil Liberties Clearing House, 1961-1963 (Box 196, Folder 10)
  - National Conference on Human Rights, 1957, 1968 (Box 196, Folder 11)
  - National Joint Community Relations Committee, 1961-1968 (Box 196, Folder 12)
  - National Office Committee, 1973 (Box 196, Folder 13)
  - Nazi War Criminals (Neo-Nazis), 1965-1967 (Box 196, Folder 14)
  - New Brunswick, undated (Box 196, Folder 15)
  - New Party, 1960-1961 (Box 196, Folder 16)
  - Nova Scotia, 1959-1967 (Box 196, Folder 17)
  - Ontario, 1965 (Box 196, Folder 18)
  - Ontario Federation of Labour, 1952-1962 (Box 196, Folder 19)
  - Ontario Human Rights Commission, 1960-1967 (Box 196, Folder 20)
  - Ontario Labour Committee for Human Rights, 1967-1969 (Box 196, Folder 21)
  - Ontario Labour Relations Board, 1961 (Box 196, Folder 22)
  - Orlikow, L., undated (Box 196, Folder 23)
  - Poland: Anti-Semitism, 1968 (Box 196, Folder 24)
  - Polish Refugees, 1968-1970 (Box 196, Folder 25)
  - Presse Ouvriere Cooperative, 1966 (Box 196, Folder 26)
  - Publicity, 1948-1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Publicity, 1957-1973 (Box 196, Folder 27)
  - Quebec, 1960-1966 (Box 196, Folder 28)
  - Quebec: Discrimination, 1962 (Box 196, Folder 29)
  - Quebec Federation of Labour, 1962-1969 (Box 196, Folder 30-31)
  - Radio Scripts, 1959 (Box 197, Folder 1)
  - Railway Employees: Discrimination Against, 1961 (Box 197, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1957-1975 (Box 197, Folder 3-4)
  - Reports (Yiddish), 1963-1973 (Box 197, Folder 5)
  - Resolutions, 1956; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Resolutions, 1961-1965 (Box 197, Folder 6)
  - Romanian Refugees, undated (Box 197, Folder 7)
  - Rubinstein, Michael, 1959-1963 (Box 197, Folder 8)
  - Saskatchewan, 1958 (Box 197, Folder 9)
  - Simon, Harry, 1974 (Box 197, Folder 10)
  - Songs, undated (Box 198, Folder 11)
  - Soviet Jewish Writers, 1971-1972 (Box 197, Folder 12)
  - Soviet Jewry, 1953; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Soviet Jewry, 1957-1978 (Box 197, Folder 13)
  - St. Leonard, 1968 (Box 197, Folder 14)
  - Syria, 1972 (Box 197, Folder 15)
  - Toronto, 1947-1956; 2 folders (Box 392)
  - Toronto, 1957-1962 (Box 197, Folder 16)
  - Trades and Labor Congress of Canada, 1952-1954; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - United Council for Human Rights, 1957-1973 (Box 198, Folder 2-4)
  - Vancouver, 1950-1954; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Vancouver, 1957-1969 (Box 198, Folder 5)
  - Vladeck Women's Club, undated (Box 198, Folder 6)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Commemorations, 1961-1973 (Box 198, Folder 7)
  - Windsor, 1953; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Winnipeg, 1947-1951; 1 folder (Box 392)
  - Winnipeg, 1957-1972 (Box 198, Folder 8)
  - Workmen's Circle, 1969 (Box 198, Folder 9)
  - Zygielbojm, Szmul (Arthur), 1968 (Box 198, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Microfilm, 1934-1979
  In the 1970s, the JLC hired Israel Figa as an archival consultant to assess the needs of its institutional archives. The 16 millimeter microfilm reels in this series are of the documents selected for filming by Figa. Boxes of the materials selected for microfilming were later transferred to the Tamiment Library, but it is possible that the microfilm includes documents that were not donated to Tamiment.
  - Microfilm by Israel Figa, circa 1934-1979; 15 Reels (Box 515)
  - Microfilm by Israel Figa, circa 1934-1979; 11 Reels (Box 516)
- Series VIII: Tamiment Library Collection of Jewish Labor Committee Records, circa 1940-1999
  This series contains Jewish Labor Committee records that were collected by or donated to Gail Malmgreen, a former Tamiment Library staff member, over a number of years, either for internal reference purposes or inclusion in the JLC Records, Parts I, II, and III. Approximately one-third of this series is comprised of biographical files on various individuals involved with the JLC. The rest of the series contains subject files on civil rights, Poland, the JLC's history, and other topics. Also of note are federal government documents on the JLC obtained from a Freedom of Information Act request and numerous pamphlets and brochures produced by the JLC and other Jewish and labor organizations. Many materials in this series are likely duplicated in other parts of the collection.
  Materials are arranged in the order in which they were discovered in the repository.
  - Assorted Subject Files, circa 1940-1999 (Box 535)
  - Biographical Files and Lists of Individuals Rescued by the JLC, circa 1940-1999 (Box 536)
  - Freedom of Information Act Documents and Assorted Subject Files, circa 1940-1999 (Box 537, Box 538)
  - Union newspapers on AFL-CIO merger, 1955-12 (Box 537)
- Series IX: Archived Website, Sep 25, 2007-ongoing
  The Jewish Labor Committee, an independent secular organization, is the voice of the Jewish community in the labor movement and the voice of the labor movement in the Jewish community. The JLC was formed in 1934 by Yiddish-speaking immigrant trade union leaders and leaders of such groups as the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, the Jewish Labor Bund, and the United Hebrew Trades, in response to the rise of Nazism in Germany. The JLC enables the Jewish community and the trade union movement to work together on important issues of shared interest and concern, in pursuit of economic and social justice. The website contains activity reports, news listings, and information on chapters.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
- Series X: Graphics and Media, 1945-2007
  - Filmstrip teachers guide: "Warsaw Ghetto: Holocaust and Resistance", 1974 (Box 540, Folder 1)
  - Graphics, leaflets, cartoons, Joe Worker comic books, 1945-2004 (Box 540, Folder 2-13, Box 541, Folder 1-5)
  - Labor Reports cartoons by Herron, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 006, Folder 8)
  - JLC meeting contact sheets, negatives, undated (Box 541, Folder 6)
  - Seder and Passover exhibit graphics, 2005, 2007 (Box 541, Folder 7, Box 542, Box 543)
  - JLC award to Harry Van Arsdale Jr., 1969 (Box 541, Folder 8)
  - Filmstrip and audiocassette: Warsaw Ghetto: Holocaust and Resistance", 1974 (Box Shared Tamiment 004)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives with collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
  - Video: "The Labor Movement and the Jews," David Schacter, Prof. Stanley Rosen, Rabbi Schallman, 1986 (Box Shared Tamiment 004)
  - DVD: "Di Kinder foun di heimen." Les maisons d' enfants parrainees par le Jewish Labor Committee, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 004)
  - Silver Jubilee--Tribute to the Organized Labor Movement and George Meany, March 1960 (Box Shared Tamiment 079, Folder 1)
  - Unprocessed Videos (Box Shared Tamiment 022)